Finding Aid for John W. Jickling papers.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
John W. Jickling papers 1860-2010 1940-2000
Jickling, John W.
2014016 Aa 2 UAl M Roll 119
Papers of Michigan architect John Ward Jickling. The collection mainly consists of Jickling's architectural projects, including correspondence and blueprints. The bulk of the collection contains papers from Jickling's involvement with the Oakland Land Conservancy and committees. In addition, the collection contains papers of his father, Clare Jickling, and his wife's father, James Fairman. It also contains a large amount of genealogy research that Jickling and his family conducted. There are photographs in the collection ranging from the mid-19th century to the early 2000s.
4.5 linear feet
2 oversize folders
1 tubes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Julia Jickling (Donor No. 10843 ) in October, 2012.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
John Ward Jickling (1921-2012) grew up in Birmingham, Michigan and graduated from the University of Michigan College of Architecture in 1948. Jickling enlisted in the U.S. Army Air Force in 1942 and was called up for service in 1943. He served at bases in Mississippi and Texas where he instructed gunnery students and acted as the architectural assistant to the Post Engineer at Harlingen Army Airfield.
Jickling married Barbara Wright Fairman (who also graduated from the University of Michigan College of Architecture) in 1947 and they moved to Birmingham, MI where Jickling worked for Swanson Associates. John left Swanson and he and Barbara founded their own architectural firm, Jickling, Lyman & Powell Associates of Troy, Michigan in 1962. Jickling was a prolific architect and designed several buildings for the University of Michigan, including the Gerald Ford Presidential Library, the Bentley Historical Library, and the Medical Research Building. In 1979 he was made a Fellow of the American Institute of Architects. In 1983 he was awarded the Gold Medal by its Detroit Chapter and in 1988 he was given a Gold medal by the Michigan Society of Architects. He served as the Regional Director of the American Institute of Architects, the President of the Michigan Society of Architects, and the President of the Detroit Chapter of the American Institute of Architects. Jickling retired from active practice in 1988 but continued to practice as a consultant until the early 2000s.
Besides his involvement with the architecture community, Jickling was a founding member of the Oakland Land Conservancy and served as a board member of the Oakland County parks Foundation from 1989-1992. He also served on the Birmingham Planning Board, the Historic District Design Review Committee, and the Historic District Study Committee.
Jickling's father and father-in-law were active members of their community as well. Clare Mason Jickling (1894-1968) attended Kalamazoo College and the University of Michigan. During World War I he served in the Army Air Corps. He and his wife, Norma Carland, lived in the Detroit area and in 1931 Clare established his own advertising firm, Wolf-Jickling-Dow.
James Fairman (1896-1967) grew up in Big Rapids, MI. In 1918 he graduated from the University of Michigan with a Bachelors of Science in Engineering. He was a Second Lieutenant in the U.S. Army at Camp Meade, Maryland. Between 1919 and 1925 Fairman taught in the College of Engineering at the University of Michigan. In 1921 he earned his Masters of Science in Engineering from the University of Michigan. Fairman worked for 37 years at the Consolidated Edison Company of New York until he retired in 1963. During his time there, he earned the nickname "Mr. Atom" for his work on an atomic powered generating plant on the Hudson River. In 1959 the American Society of Electrical Engineers awarded Fairman the Edison Gold Medal for his "outstanding performance in improving the design of large electric power systems; for far-sighted leadership in atomic power development; and for unremitting efforts to improve the engineering profession."
The collection mainly consists of Jickling's architectural projects, including correspondence and blueprints. The bulk of the collection contains papers from Jickling's involvement with the Oakland Land Conservancy and committees. In addition, the collection contains papers of his father, Clare Jickling, and his wife's father, James Fairman. It also contains a large amount of genealogy research that Jickling and his family conducted. There are photographs in the collection ranging from the mid-19th century to the early 2000s. The collection consists of three series: Professional (2 linear feet and 2 outsize folders), Personal (1.5 linear feet and a tube), and Photographs (1 linear foot).
Subjects:
Fairman, James F., (James Ferdinand), 1896-1967.; Jickling, Clare Mason.; Jickling, John W.; Architects--Michigan.; Architecture--Michigan.; Birmingham (Mich.); Christ Land Conservancy (Mich.); Oakland Land Conservancy (Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Jickling, John W.; Jickling family.
Genre Terms:
Architectural drawings.; CD-ROMs.; Color negatives.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Professional
  The Professional series contains information on Jickling's architectural projects and architectural associations/firms of which he was a member. There is information on the firm he founded, Jickling, Lyman & Powell, including meeting minutes, brochures, corporate resolutions, and stockholder's agreements. The assorted projects folder includes: drawings for Woodfield Mall in Schaumburg, Illinois; a news release for Birmingham's first exposed steel parking structure, which involved Jickling's firm; and a directory of The Mall at Short Hills, New Jersey, with markings possibly made by Jickling. There is also about half a linear foot and two outsize folders of Jickling's architectural projects. These include drawings, blueprints, and correspondence concerning the structures. The unidentified folder contains drawings with no label. Jickling's involvement with Christ Church Cranbrook is professional and personal in nature. Large architectural drawings are included within the outsize folder. However, his other works-both professional and personal-are in their own category, "Christ Church Cranbrook."
  Besides architectural work, the Professional series includes information on Jickling's community involvement. Approximately half a linear foot contains reports and publications of the City of Birmingham, of which Jickling was a member of various boards. There are also records of the Michigan Architectural Foundation, including minutes, bylaws, and financial statements. The bulk of the series contains information on the Oakland Land Conservancy, including correspondence, easement information, newsletters, and maps. For both the Michigan Architectural Foundation and the Oakland Land Conservancy, the "founding documents" folder contains documents such as mission and vision statements of the organization.
  - American Institute of Architects (Box 1)
  - Architectural Firms
    - Jickling, Lyman & Powell
      - Assorted Projects (Box 1)
      - Board of Directors annual meeting minutes 1986-1995 (Box 1)
      - Brochure (Box 1)
      - Corporate resolutions 1986-1987 (Box 1)
      - Memorandums 1972, 1989 (Box 1)
      - Newspaper articles (Box 1)
      - Promotion (Box 1)
      - Stockholder's Agreements 1972-1995 (Box 1)
    - Swanson Associates, Inc.
      - Brochure (Box 1)
      - Project reports (Box 1)
  - Architectural Projects
    - Anne Rumsey Weston residence (Box 1)
    - Architectural Commission-Episcopal Diocese of Michigan (Box 1)
    - Assorted churches (Box 1)
    - Clare Jickling residence (Box 1)
    - Coalition on Temporary Shelter (COTS) (Box 1)
    - Episcopal Diocesan Center (Box 1)
    - Family cottage (Box 1)
    - Interior model (Box 1)
    - John Jickling residence (Box 1)
    - Lakeshore Presbyterian (Box 1)
    - Lamont residence (Box 1)
    - Lotz residence (Box 1)
    - Roosevelt School (Box 1)
    - St. Andrew's Episcopal Church (Box 1)
    - University of Michigan Medical Science Research Building III (Box 1)
    - Unidentified (Box 1)
  - Christ Church Cranbrook
    - Artworks Committee (Box 1)
    - Black Manifesto (Box 1)
    - Improvement projects, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - City of Birmingham
    - Birmingham Estates Garden Club research project (Box 1)
    - Civic Center Improvement project (Box 1)
    - Family Preparedness Workbook (Box 1)
    - Historic District Study Committee-Birmingham, MI, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Urban Design Plans 1929-1963 scattered, 2 of 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Urban Design Plans 1929-1963 scattered, 2 of 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Michigan Architectural Foundation
    - Articles of Incorporation (Box 2)
    - Beaubien House Committee, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Bylaws (Box 2)
    - Financial statements 1981-1990 (Box 2)
    - Founding documents (Box 2)
    - Michigan Architectural Foundation and Michigan Society of Architects agreement 1987 (Box 2)
    - Minutes 1988-1990 (Box 2)
  - Oakland Land Conservancy
    - Agreements of cooperation and affiliation (Box 2)
    - Correspondence
      - Jickling, John 1990s 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Tomboulian, Alice 1990s (Box 2)
    - Declaration of conservation easement (Box 2)
    - Founding documents (Box 2)
    - Grand Traverse Regional Land Conservancy (Box 2)
    - Maps (Box 2)
    - Meeting minutes 1994-1996 (Box 2)
    - Newsletters 1995-1997 (Box 2)
    - Newspaper articles (Box 2)
    - Oakland County (Box 2)
    - Photographs, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Properties
      - Battaglia (Box 2)
      - Fanuc (Box 2)
      - Frankel, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Springfield Township superfund site (Box 2)
    - Reports, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Architectural Center for a state university (Folder 1)
  - Class sketches 1940s (Folder 1)
  - Hidden Valley Lake and Beach Club 1948 (Folder 1)
  - Holy Cross Episcopal Mission, Novi, MI-1966 1994 (Folder 1)
  - Jickling residence 1954 (Folder 1)
  - Jickling residence storage expansion 1972 (Folder 1)
  - Job No. 4914 Swanson Associates (Folder 1)
  - McLouth Steel Corporation proposed administration building 1948 (Folder 1)
  - Oakland County Natural Areas Inventory 1986-1988 (Folder 1)
  - Roadside nursery stand, Arch. 10 summer session 1947 (Folder 1)
  - Simmon's Orchard storm sewer plan (Folder 1)
  - Springs Cotton Mills 1948 (Folder 1)
  - St. Andrews Episcopal Church, Ann Arbor, MI 1949 (Folder 1)
  - St. Paul's Episcopal Church, Romeo, MI (Folder 1)
  - Swanson Associates, perspective view (Folder 1)
  - Briggs Building expansion (Folder 2)
  - Christ Church, Grosse Pointe Farms 1928 (Folder 2)
  - Christ Church Cranbrook-1983 1987, 1991, 1998 (Folder 2)
  - Diocesan Center second floor plan 1995 (Folder 2)
- Personal
  The Personal series contains Jickling's personal correspondence, James Fairman's papers, Clare Jickling's papers, genealogy information, and photographs. The "assorted" folder in the correspondence section contains letters from various friends, family members, and unidentified individuals. The correspondence section also includes Barbara Jickling's letters to people besides Jickling. The "undated" folder contains correspondence between Barbara and John Jickling. Jickling's letters home during his time in the military are also included in this section.
  The James Fairman section contains biographical articles that were published in newspapers and engineering newsletters. There are also folders of correspondence between Fairman and his wife, Bertha, and Barbara Jickling, his daughter. The miscellaneous folder contains a portrait photograph, editorial, a newsletter, stock certificate of the Fairman Electric Light and Power Co. (1897), and Fairman's funeral pamphlet. It also contains a deposit ticket from the 1890s of Fairman and Newton, Bankers and an 1880s stock certificate of the Big Rapids Woodenware Company.
  The Clare Jickling section contains Clare's personal correspondence, his will, and information on his military service during World War I. There are also records of Ralph L. Wolfe and Associates, where Clare served on the first board of directors. These records include bylaws and meeting minutes. Clare's section also includes three diaries of Norma Jickling (Carland), his wife. There are numerous philatelist brochures ranging from the 1890s to the 1930s that were published in various locations. Michigan philatelist brochures include the Michigan Philatelist (1909-1910) and The Michigan Stamp (1895). Some of the advertising brochures, entitled "Money," were written by C. M. Jickling.
  The series also contains a section of genealogy research that John Jickling conducted. Jickling was an avid genealogist and published multiple volumes about his family from Comstock, Michigan and from Norfolk, England. There are also a few folders dedicated to the Fairman family. The "Jickling research" folders contain notes and correspondence between John Jickling and David Jickling about their research. There are several family trees, one of which is about six feet long and stored in a tube. The Y2K Family Yearbook contains an accompanying CD-ROM. This section also contains the "Jickling Journal," which is a family newsletter written by John Jickling.
  - Correspondence
    - Annual family newsletters 1997, 2003 (Box 3)
    - Assorted 1960s-1980s (Box 3)
    - Jickling, Alex and Ella 1963-1982 (Box 3)
    - Jickling, Barbara 1960s-1970s (Box 3)
      (her letters)
    - Jickling, Barbara undated (Box 3)
    - Jickling, Clare 1966, undated (Box 3)
    - Jickling, David 1982-1983 (Box 3)
    - Jickling, David 1970s-1980s, 2 folders (Box 3)
      (of Augusta, MI)
    - Jickling, John 1943 (Box 3)
    - Locke, Jean 1960s-1970s (Box 3)
    - Mackenzie, Daphne undated (Box 3)
    - Stifler, John 1968 (Box 3)
  - Pilot logs 1943-1944 (Box 3)
  - James F. Fairman
    - Biographical articles (Box 3)
    - Correspondence
      - Fairman (Wright), Bertha 1919-1929, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Jickling (Fairman), Barbara 1940s-1970s, 12 folders (Box 3)
      - Trowbridge 1907, 1915 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Clare Jickling
    - Brochures
      - Advertising brochures, C.M. Jickling 1932 (Box 3)
      - Life insurance brochures, R.L. Jickling 1927-1934 (Box 3)
      - Philatelist brochures 1890s-1930s (Box 3)
    - Correspondence
      - Carland, W.W. 1920 (Box 3)
      - D.E. Brewer Associates, Inc. 1964-1965 (Box 3)
      - Jickling, Norma and W.W. Carland 1921 (Box 3)
      - Jickling, R. Lee 1947, 1960s (Box 3)
      - Woodburne, Russell T., University of Michigan professor, Department of Anatomy 1957 (Box 3)
    - Jickling (Carland), Norma diaries-1918 1920, 1923 (Box 3)
    - Last Will and Testament (Box 3)
    - Military service, World War I, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Ralph L. Wolfe and Associates, Inc. records (Box 3)
  - Genealogy
    - Centennial Remembrance of Robert Lee Jickling 1989 (Box 3)
    - Charts, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Charts, 5 pages (Tube 1)
    - Fairman family, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Fairman, Blackman family (Box 4)
    - Jickling, Catherine and William (Box 4)
    - Jicklings of Comstock, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Jickling family directory (Box 4)
    - Jickling family history (Box 4)
    - Jickling Journal 1998-2001 (Box 4)
    - Jickling (Metz), Margaret Catherine (Box 4)
    - Jicklings of Norfolk, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Jickling research, 7 folders (Box 4)
    - Mason family (Box 4)
    - Newell, Richard Harry (Box 4)
    - Parker, Strong, Atherton family (Box 4)
    - Whitney 1860s (Box 4)
    - Y2K Jickling Family Yearbook, includes CD-ROM, 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series includes photographs ranging from the mid-19th century to the early 2000s. Many of them are of the Jickling family. There are two scrapbooks in the series. One dates from the early 1900s and the other includes photographs from the late 19th-early 20th century. Finally, the series contains negatives from a family event.
  - Negatives 1998 (Box 4)
  - Photographs, 12 of 22 folders (Box 4)
  - Photographs, 10 of 22 folders (Box 5)
  - Scrapbooks, 2 folders (Box 5)